<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Old Dog Gone Off Trail</title>
    <link href="https://offtrail.guru/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://offtrail.guru" />
    <updated>2023-10-07T09:25:25+02:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Patrick</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://offtrail.guru</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Travel Bookings To Balconia</title>
        <author>
            <name>Patrick</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://offtrail.guru/travel-bookings-to-balconia/"/>
        <id>https://offtrail.guru/travel-bookings-to-balconia/</id>
        <media:content url="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/78/balconia-00-2.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="travel"/>
            <category term="cycling"/>
            <category term="blog post"/>

        <updated>2023-09-16T16:41:01+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/78/balconia-00-2.jpg" alt="Climbing the Grenchenberg" />
                    <p class="dropcap">The last time my wife and I traveled was in October 2017. We drove to Nice to meet an American friend who happened to spend a few days there. We used the trip to <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/collideous/37258753184" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nice</a> to visit a bunch of wineries in the Rhône Valley. On the way back, we crossed the border into Italy for a winery tour through the Piedmont region. A drive across the Great St Bernard pass brought us back to Switzerland. We have not spent any vacations abroad or within Switzerland since. Seeing how one natural disaster is following the next on our ever-hotter planet, who can still travel with a good conscience today? Travel by air or by car is a luxury only a few on this planet can even afford. It’s a First World luxury and not a necessity. For a healthier planet and the future of generations to come, we should honestly do without.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/78/balconia-00-2.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Climbing the Grenchenberg" /></p>
                <p class="dropcap">The last time my wife and I traveled was in October 2017. We drove to Nice to meet an American friend who happened to spend a few days there. We used the trip to <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/collideous/37258753184" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nice</a> to visit a bunch of wineries in the Rhône Valley. On the way back, we crossed the border into Italy for a winery tour through the Piedmont region. A drive across the Great St Bernard pass brought us back to Switzerland. We have not spent any vacations abroad or within Switzerland since. Seeing how one natural disaster is following the next on our ever-hotter planet, who can still travel with a good conscience today? Travel by air or by car is a luxury only a few on this planet can even afford. It’s a First World luxury and not a necessity. For a healthier planet and the future of generations to come, we should honestly do without.</p>

<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="3">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/78/gallery/balconia-01.jpg" data-size="4096x3072"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/78/gallery/balconia-01-thumbnail.webp" alt="Climbing the Grenchenberg." width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Grenchenberg.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/78/gallery/balconia-02.jpg" data-size="4096x2304"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/78/gallery/balconia-02-thumbnail.webp" alt="Returning to Romont." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Romont.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/78/gallery/balconia-03.jpg" data-size="3106x1747"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/78/gallery/balconia-03-thumbnail.webp" alt="Climbing the Bettlachbergstrasse." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Bettlachbergstrasse.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>Lately, my blog has focused more on equipment and gear than rides because I do all my riding from home. I have not been able to spend the time I would like on the saddle, so rides aren’t long nor particularly adventurous. So, there just isn’t much interesting to report about. This past seven days, I took a staycation and took advantage of the dry, sunny conditions to hit the trails on my <a href="https://offtrail.guru/stooge-mk5/">Stooge</a>. While some days were at my heat limit, I got out for 3-hour rides daily. The trails were spectacular. Looking at the leaf-covered ground, one felt like being in the middle of autumn. Looking at the foliage, though, autumn seems nowhere yet. That isn’t good. The forests at our latitudes aren’t used to the kind of heat we’re experiencing, and they’re suffering from heat stress. It remains to be seen if our trees are going to carry the beautiful fall colors that they should in the weeks to come or if they’re going to drop their foliage as rapidly as some already have.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="3">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/78/gallery/balconia-04.jpg" data-size="4096x2636"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/78/gallery/balconia-04-thumbnail.webp" alt="Riding along the Bözingenberg." width="720" height="463"></a>
<figcaption>Bözingenberg.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/78/gallery/balconia-05.jpg" data-size="4096x2926"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/78/gallery/balconia-05-thumbnail.webp" alt="Climbing the Bözingenberg." width="720" height="514"></a>
<figcaption>Bözingenberg.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/78/gallery/balconia-06.jpg" data-size="3881x2183"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/78/gallery/balconia-06-thumbnail.webp" alt="Crossing the Bözingenberg." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Bözingenberg.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>I’ll return to share a few bike updates In the coming weeks and months. I already mentioned in a <a href="https://offtrail.guru/first-200km-on-my-gestalt-x12/">recent post</a> that XPLR is the perfect drivetrain for my road and gravel rides. So, there are a couple of things on my todo list:</p>
<h6>Nordest Albarda:</h6>
<ul>
<li>Install a 5-bolt 110BCD spider and FlatTop compatible <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/collideous/53172808983" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">42T oval</a> chainring ☑️</li>
<li>Remove SRAM Red AXS front derailleur ☑️</li>
<li>Replace the 30mm BSA bottom bracket ☑️</li>
<li>Replace the 2.5mm offset Rotor <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/collideous/52654489853" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">road axle</a> with a shorter standard axle ☑️</li>
<li>Replace SRAM Force FlatTop chain</li>
<li>Install SRAM Red XPLR AXS rear derailleur instead of the standard one</li>
</ul>
<h6>Volagi Viaje:</h6>
<ul>
<li>Install a 5-bolt 110BCD spider and FlatTop compatible <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/collideous/53172524179" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">44T oval</a> chainring ☑️</li>
<li>Remove SRAM Red eTap front derailleur ☑️</li>
<li>Replace Industry 9 Torch HG-type freehub body with an XDR freehub</li>
<li>Install SRAM XPLR 10-44T cassette</li>
<li>Install SRAM Force FlatTop chain</li>
<li>Install SRAM Force XPLR AXS rear derailleur instead of the old one</li>
<li>Install SRAM Force AXS shift/brake levers instead of the old Red eTap ones</li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Summers Are Getting Shorter</title>
        <author>
            <name>Patrick</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://offtrail.guru/summers-are-getting-shorter/"/>
        <id>https://offtrail.guru/summers-are-getting-shorter/</id>
        <media:content url="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/77/shorter-summers-00.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="climate change"/>
            <category term="blog post"/>

        <updated>2023-08-26T09:01:50+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/77/shorter-summers-00.jpg" alt="Road between Frinvillier and Péry." />
                    <p class="dropcap">As climate change is lengthening summers and making them frighteningly hotter, summers for cyclists or anyone else exercising outdoors, for that matter, are already getting a lot shorter. The two heatwaves that hit Switzerland's northern half shortened my 2023 summer cycling already by a whole month in which I was off the bike. In those four weeks, I didn’t exercise at all and spent little time outdoors. I only caught a bit of fresh air, if one can even call it "fresh" when I sat under our sun shades on the balcony with my laptop and a cold <a href="https://lagunitas.com/beer/ipa/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lagunitas IPA</a>. Instead of hitting the road or climbing trails, weekends were spent inside watching Netflix or Apple TV.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/77/shorter-summers-00.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Road between Frinvillier and Péry." /></p>
                <p class="dropcap">As climate change is lengthening summers and making them frighteningly hotter, summers for cyclists or anyone else exercising outdoors, for that matter, are already getting a lot shorter. The two heatwaves that hit Switzerland's northern half shortened my 2023 summer cycling already by a whole month in which I was off the bike. In those four weeks, I didn’t exercise at all and spent little time outdoors. I only caught a bit of fresh air, if one can even call it "fresh" when I sat under our sun shades on the balcony with my laptop and a cold <a href="https://lagunitas.com/beer/ipa/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lagunitas IPA</a>. Instead of hitting the road or climbing trails, weekends were spent inside watching Netflix or Apple TV.</p>

<p>I’ve noticed on <a href="https://www.strava.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Strava</a> that many cyclists I follow, who take their training more seriously, have switched to riding indoors. It was rare to see a <a href="https://www.zwift.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Zwift</a> activity during the summer months just a year or two ago. Most switch to training indoors when the days get shorter and colder. Now, a considerable number of cyclists trained indoors because the summer of 2023 was too damn hot.</p>
<p>Cycling, for me, has to be fun, enjoyable, and healthy. Once the thermometer passes 25°C, these three things start to dive, and the higher the relative humidity, the quicker they dive. If the air is dry, it can remain enjoyable at 30+°C. But if it’s muggy, the fun is gone. I also put great importance to only doing what benefits my health, and exercising in the heat is anything but healthy. On the contrary, you unnecessarily stress your body, even damage it, and in the worst case, put yourself in danger.<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>A strenuous bike ride can already become dangerous at 30°C and a relative humidity above 55%. <a href="https://arielschecklist.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ariel's Checklist</a>, a website with safety guidelines for hiking in the desert, has a tremendous <a href="https://arielschecklist.com/wbgt-chart/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">wet bulb temperature chart</a> showing the danger of physical activity at different combinations of temperature and humidity. I don't need to check the chart. I wouldn't even leave the house when conditions reach the red levels.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy"  src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/77/shorter-summers-01-2.jpg" alt="Wet Bulb Temperature Chart" width="1105" height="887" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/77/responsive/shorter-summers-01-2-xs.webp 300w ,https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/77/responsive/shorter-summers-01-2-sm.webp 480w ,https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/77/responsive/shorter-summers-01-2-md.webp 768w ,https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/77/responsive/shorter-summers-01-2-lg.webp 1024w ,https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/77/responsive/shorter-summers-01-2-xl.webp 1360w ,https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/77/responsive/shorter-summers-01-2-2xl.webp 1600w"><figcaption>Source: <a href="https://arielschecklist.com/wbgt-chart/">https://arielschecklist.com/wbgt-chart/</a></figcaption></figure>
<p>2023 has been a scary year. Heat waves have paralyzed the American South from east to west. It has hit large parts of Asia, the Middle East, as well as Europe, particularly the Mediterranean. Huge wildfires engulfed Canada, Portugal, Greece, and tropical Hawaii, where the fire that destroyed Lahaina became the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2023_Hawaii_wildfires#Casualties" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">deadliest</a> US blaze in a century. Heat waves also always lead to heavy thunderstorms and flooding. There have been floods in India, Mongolia, California, Slovenia, Italy, and Norway, to name a few. As we're in an <a href="https://www.weather.gov/news/230706-ElNino" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">El Niño</a> year, this will continue well into 2024. El Niño transports humidity away from Asia and Australia to North and South America. When <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Effects_of_the_El_Ni%C3%B1o%E2%80%93Southern_Oscillation_in_Australia#El_Ni%C3%B1o" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Australia</a> heads into summer, that continent will be a tinderbox. The US West Coast will see lots of floods. Living in California, I experienced El Niño in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1997%E2%80%9398_El_Ni%C3%B1o_event" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">1997-1998</a>. It was regarded as one of the most powerful El Niño Southern Oscillation events in recorded history. And it was quite bad. At the same time, oceans across the globe have reached surface temperatures like we have never seen before. The August heat wave pushed the zero-degree line in the Swiss Alps to <a href="https://www.meteoschweiz.admin.ch/ueber-uns/meteoschweiz-blog/de/2023/08/die-rekorde-purzeln.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">5,298 meters</a> above sea level. In other words, every alpine glacier was melting.</p>
<p>I don't think mankind is going to reverse the civilization-ending trajectory it’s on. Science has known since the 50ies what will happen to the planet when humans burn fossil fuels. The public has been well aware of it since the 80ies. Forty years later, we have done shit about it. People think that governments will somehow fix it. In the meantime, they fly across the globe for a Christmas holiday on a beach in Thailand or board a plane for a shopping weekend in New York. Rather than downsizing, our homes and cars are only getting bigger. The capitalist system that we live in demands that we consume more and more. A larger flat-screen TV every couple of years, a new cell phone every year, new clothes every few months; it's oil to keep our economy running smoothly. Without growth, it would collapse. We're depleting our planet’s resources and heating up its precious atmosphere. I used to think that it'll take a couple more generations until mankind is going to be in trouble. Not anymore. These events are upon us much faster, and we’ll experience them on our own skin.</p>
<p>In the coming years, natural disasters caused by the climate catastrophe are going to burden First World economies heavily. Heat waves will kill those without the luxury of air-conditioning. The number of refugees currently crossing the Mediterranean Sea will be dwarfed by the millions of climate refugees who will be forced to leave large <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/climate-environment/2022/10/11/extreme-heat-heatwave-deaths/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">uninhabitable</a>, equatorial regions in Africa, India, and elsewhere. Europe won’t be welcoming but become a fortress. The Swiss forests I enjoy on my bike, <a href="https://www.bafu.admin.ch/bafu/en/home/topics/forest/in-brief.html#:~:text=The%20hot%2C%20dry%20summers%20of,extremes%20or%20even%20died%20off." target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">unable to cope</a> with the heat, will start dying off. Like elsewhere in the world, our forests will burn, too. Our water supply will no longer be guaranteed when our <a href="https://www.swissinfo.ch/eng/society/swiss-glacier-series--0-1-000m-_melting-swiss-glaciers-to-fuel-conflicts-over-water-/45371008" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">alpine glaciers</a> are gone. Without enough water, farming will become increasingly difficult. And to come back to cycling, summers will be three months of <a href="https://www.zwift.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Zwift</a> with the AC on full power, provided the power grid doesn’t collapse.</p>
<p>Maybe you say, “Oh, Patrick, you’re a pessimist.” I don’t think so. I’m a realist. Forty years ago, there was still time to be optimistic. To be optimistic today is to live in a fantasy. We’re not willing to change our destructive lifestyles. We want our vacations, we want our homes, we want our cars, and we want our stuff. A world on fire won’t change us. Maybe it’ll change our children or grandchildren if they manage to survive, but certainly not us.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>First 200km On My Gestalt X12</title>
        <author>
            <name>Patrick</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://offtrail.guru/first-200km-on-my-gestalt-x12/"/>
        <id>https://offtrail.guru/first-200km-on-my-gestalt-x12/</id>
        <media:content url="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/first-200km-00.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="gravel bikes"/>
            <category term="geometry"/>
            <category term="blog post"/>

        <updated>2023-08-08T14:35:25+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/first-200km-00.jpg" alt="Marin Gestalt X12 on the Grenchenberg." />
                    <p class="dropcap">With a fleet of six bikes, of which three are surface-agnostic SUBs, commonly better known as gravel, all-road, or adventure bikes, I didn’t need another one this year. But when I first spotted the <a href="https://www.marinbikes.com/bikes/2023-gestalt-x10" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Marin Gestalt X10</a> last November, I knew I had to get one. The bike is slacker than my FortyFour mountain bikes, with a 67.5º head angle. Reach is 63mm longer than my <a href="https://offtrail.guru/nordest-albarda/">Nordest Albarda</a> and 68mm longer than my <a href="https://offtrail.guru/volagi-viaje-sl/">Volagi Viaje</a>. The Gestalt’s wheelbase is 95mm greater than the Nordest and an enormous 124mm more than the Volagi. It’s a massively <a href="https://offtrail.guru/the-geometry-of-a-gravel-bike/">different bike</a>. And that’s the reason I bought one. Some time down the road, I’d love to design the perfect SUB frame for myself. It only makes sense to go down that path with years of cycling under one’s belt, which I have, and countless hours spent on a wide range of bikes. And that one can never have enough.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/first-200km-00.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Marin Gestalt X12 on the Grenchenberg." /></p>
                <p class="dropcap">With a fleet of six bikes, of which three are surface-agnostic SUBs, commonly better known as gravel, all-road, or adventure bikes, I didn’t need another one this year. But when I first spotted the <a href="https://www.marinbikes.com/bikes/2023-gestalt-x10" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Marin Gestalt X10</a> last November, I knew I had to get one. The bike is slacker than my FortyFour mountain bikes, with a 67.5º head angle. Reach is 63mm longer than my <a href="https://offtrail.guru/nordest-albarda/">Nordest Albarda</a> and 68mm longer than my <a href="https://offtrail.guru/volagi-viaje-sl/">Volagi Viaje</a>. The Gestalt’s wheelbase is 95mm greater than the Nordest and an enormous 124mm more than the Volagi. It’s a massively <a href="https://offtrail.guru/the-geometry-of-a-gravel-bike/">different bike</a>. And that’s the reason I bought one. Some time down the road, I’d love to design the perfect SUB frame for myself. It only makes sense to go down that path with years of cycling under one’s belt, which I have, and countless hours spent on a wide range of bikes. And that one can never have enough.</p>

<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="4">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-01.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-01-thumbnail.webp" alt="Evening ride to the Grenchenberg." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Grenchenberg.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-04.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-04-thumbnail.webp" alt="Another visit to the Grenchenberg." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Grenchenberg.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-02.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-02-thumbnail.webp" alt="Evening ride to the Grenchenberg." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Grenchenberg.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-03.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-03-thumbnail.webp" alt="Evening ride to the Grenchenberg." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Grenchenberg.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>Visually, I love the result. I purposely purchased a large frame. The 440mm reach and 175mm head tube, in combination with a <a href="https://www.syntace.com/en_GB/products/stems/mountain-bike/2988/flatforce-44" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Syntace FlatForce 44</a> stem, placed the handlebar where I needed it to be. Having the right look is nice, but optics ultimately don’t matter. A bike has to deliver. And that it does. Built as it is, the bike weighs 8.9 kilograms. Climbing out of the saddle with my hands on the hoods, the Gestalt tackles every climb in a neutral manner. It swings from side to side perfectly harmoniously with my body movement without veering left and right with every pull on the bar. When going downhill, the bike feels fast yet safe. It requires more rider input to initiate a change of direction, but I like controlling a bike with a bit of aggression. It doesn’t offer the best aero position with a 46cm wide gravel bar, but I’m out to have fun and not to win a time trial.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="4">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-05.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-05-thumbnail.webp" alt="Ride to the Romontberg." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Romontberg.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-06.jpg" data-size="3598x2024"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-06-thumbnail.webp" alt="Climbing up the Romontberg." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Romontberg.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-07.jpg" data-size="3169x1783"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-07-thumbnail.webp" alt="Last turn before the top of the Romontberg." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Romontberg.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-08.jpg" data-size="4096x2304"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/76/gallery/first-200km-08-thumbnail.webp" alt="Upper section of the Romontberg climb." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Romontberg.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>From 2015 to 2018, I took the first crack at riding 1x11 with SRAM Force CX1 on two different <a href="https://offtrail.guru/old-gravel-bikes/">bikes</a>. For most gravel rides, it was okay, but it lacked the gearing range with an 11-32T cassette. On very steep gravel climbs, I was missing a small gear, and on paved flats, I could have pushed a bigger gear. When I replaced my black Volagi Viaje CX with the Nordest Albarda, I went back to two chainrings up front. SRAM’s 1x12 <a href="https://www.sram.com/en/sram/xplr" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">XPLR drivetrain</a> in the flavors Red, Force, or Rival extends the <a href="https://www.sram.com/en/sram/xplr/xplr?filters=cattype|Cassettes&amp;sort=&amp;page=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">cassette</a> both ways (10-44T). Combined with a 42T chainring, I now feel like I have the gear range to ride everywhere. Years ago, I preferred the tight gear steps of smaller cassettes. I no longer mind the larger gear jumps of a 12-speed XPLR cassette. I often didn’t find the right cog with the old 11-32T cassette in climbs. I don't seem to have that problem on the wider XPLR cassette now. It’s been such a positive experience that I’m going to convert my Nordest Albarda and my Volagi Viaje to 1x12 as well. The Nordest will be first at the end of the year. The Volagi will follow in the spring of 2024.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Marin Gestalt X12</title>
        <author>
            <name>Patrick</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://offtrail.guru/marin-gestalt-x12/"/>
        <id>https://offtrail.guru/marin-gestalt-x12/</id>
        <media:content url="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/marin-gestalt-x12-00.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="gravel bikes"/>
            <category term="bike"/>

        <updated>2023-10-07T09:25:25+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/marin-gestalt-x12-00.jpg" alt="Marin Gestalt X12" />
                    <p class="dropcap">If it ain’t broke, don’t fix it - If something is reasonably successful or effective, there is no need to change it. German speakers would say “<i>Bewährtes soll man nicht verändern</i>.” When it comes to cycling, most of us often stick to that. We ride something, like it, and we’re therefore rarely willing to change it. I have for a long time ridden the same type of road bike. There were incremental changes such as more gears and lighter and more aero frames, but in the grand scheme of things, these improvements weren’t all that world-shattering. That changed with my first <a href="https://offtrail.guru/volagi-viaje-sl/">Volagi Viaje</a>. I started exploring things outside what is considered a “road bike.”</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/marin-gestalt-x12-00.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Marin Gestalt X12" /></p>
                <p class="dropcap">If it ain’t broke, don’t fix it - If something is reasonably successful or effective, there is no need to change it. German speakers would say “<i>Bewährtes soll man nicht verändern</i>.” When it comes to cycling, most of us often stick to that. We ride something, like it, and we’re therefore rarely willing to change it. I have for a long time ridden the same type of road bike. There were incremental changes such as more gears and lighter and more aero frames, but in the grand scheme of things, these improvements weren’t all that world-shattering. That changed with my first <a href="https://offtrail.guru/volagi-viaje-sl/">Volagi Viaje</a>. I started exploring things outside what is considered a “road bike.”</p>

<p>Without fixation on grams and watts and without having to worry about keeping up in a group ride, my view on the “ideal” road bike has evolved. Today, I take a different approach to cycling and say “If it ain’t broke, break it.” The Volagi Viajes and the <a href="https://offtrail.guru/nordest-albarda/">Nordest Albarda</a> were mostly about discovering wider tires and smaller wheels. I went from <a href="https://offtrail.guru/40-is-the-new-28/">28mm to 38mm</a> and landed at 48mm wide tires. To fit this tire width and to keep the bikes lively and agile, I swapped 700C wheels <a href="https://offtrail.guru/nordest-albarda-on-650b/">for 650B</a>. The Nordest was a first sniff at a slacker frame geometry in combination with a lower bottom bracket. The Marin Gestalt X12 however, allowed me to throw everything I know overboard. It’s a gravel bike, unlike any other gravel bike I’ve ridden. It has a <a href="https://offtrail.guru/the-geometry-of-a-gravel-bike/">geometry</a> that heavily borrows from a modern mountain bike. Its head tube angle is slacker than any of my mountain bikes. It has a long reach, a short stem, and a long wheelbase. I also set it up with a wider handlebar than what I’ve ridden up to now.</p>
<p> </p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="4">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-01.jpg" data-size="3757x2113"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-01-thumbnail.webp" alt="Marin Gestalt X12." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Marin Gestalt X12.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-04.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-04-thumbnail.webp" alt="Rotor Aldhu crankset and Wolf Tooth chainring." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Oval chainring.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-02.jpg" data-size="3512x1976"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-02-thumbnail.webp" alt="Marin Gestalt X12 from the side." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Side shot.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-03.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-03-thumbnail.webp" alt="Bottom bracket area." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Bottom bracket.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>Road.cc recently ran a feature on the rising cost of cycling. An <a href="https://www.specialized.com/ch/de/s-works-tarmac-sl7---shimano-dura-ace-di2/p/199463" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">S-Works Tarmac SL7</a> or a <a href="https://www.trekbikes.com/ch/de_CH/bikes/rennr%C3%A4der/performance-rennr%C3%A4der/madone/madone-slr/madone-slr-9-axs-gen-7/p/37420/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Trek Madone SLR 9</a> can cost you upwards of CHF 15’000.00. On the gravel side of things, you have the <a href="https://www.specialized.com/ch/en/diverge-str-pro/p/200577" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">S-Works Diverge STR</a> with an SRAM Red/XX1 mullet setup setting you back CHF 10’000.00. As a young whippersnapper, I would have lusted over these financially out-of-reach bikes. Now in my mid-fifties, such outrageously expensive bikes no longer spark my interest. Could I afford one? Yeah, I could! Would I? No, that money is better invested in my retirement account. Cycling is more fun on equipment far cheaper than that. I would even argue that if you sell one of your kidneys for a high-end bike, you will never be honest with yourself about the quality of the bike. It will be the best bike you have owned, even if it causes you back pain and rides terribly. If an inexpensive bike turns out to be a poor fit, you will have no problem admitting it to yourself or your riding buddies.</p>
<p> </p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="4">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-05.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-05-thumbnail.webp" alt="Bottom bracket area from below." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>BB area.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-06.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-06-thumbnail.webp" alt="SRAM XPLR all-steel cassette." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>All-steel cassette.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-07.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-07-thumbnail.webp" alt="SRAM Rival XPLR AXS derailleur." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Rival derailleur.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-08.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-08-thumbnail.webp" alt="Front hub and brake rotor." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Jagwire rotor.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>The good news is that there are still companies out there that try to package fun into affordability. They do so without silly technical gimmicks or claimed aerodynamic improvements but with simple bikes that try nothing more than put a smile on a rider’s face. And when I’m on a bike that’s what truly counts, not grams and watts. One such company is <a href="https://www.marinbikes.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Marin</a>. As someone who got into mountain biking in the mid-eighties, Marin is a familiar name. The company has its roots in that era, and its bikes were quite popular at the time. To be honest, Marin sort of disappeared off my radar screen. One recent day, while googling for gravel bikes with slacker head tube angles, I came across Marin’s <a href="https://www.marinbikes.com/bikes/2023-gestalt-x10" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2023 Gestalt X10</a>. I loved it at first sight. The frame geometry, the tube shapes, the tire clearance, the colors, and particularly the price. Browsing their whole catalog of bike offerings, I discovered that that’s what they do nowadays - affordable and attractive no-nonsense bikes for cyclists who cannot throw the entirety of their disposable incomes at their hobby.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="4">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-09.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-09-thumbnail.webp" alt="Syntace FlatForce 44 stem." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Syntace stem.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-10.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-10-thumbnail.webp" alt="Low and short." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Low and short.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-11.jpg" data-size="3654x2055"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-11-thumbnail.webp" alt="Syntace TwinFix mount." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>TwinFix.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-12.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/67/gallery/marin-gestalt-x12-12-thumbnail.webp" alt="Vincero Design edgePRO bottle mount." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Vincero edgePRO.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>The Gestalt X10 can be purchased for CHF 1'629.00. At that price, it comes with mechanical disc brakes by Tektro, a MicroSHIFT Advent X 10-speed derailleur, and an aluminum handlebar, seat post, and rims. It’s not a bike that would catch anyone’s interest in Switzerland because none of the components say Shimano or SRAM. And without an additional zero to its price tag, it’s a cheap man’s bike in this nation anyway. In fact, when I contacted the bike shop about it, they said they wouldn’t stock it because of the mechanical disc brakes. Swiss cyclists apparently only want hydraulic brakes. While I prefer hydraulic disc brakes for the hilly Jura, I had two bikes with <a href="https://www.flickr.com/search/?user_id=77168304%40N00&amp;view_all=1&amp;text=spyre" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">TRP Spyre</a> brakes. On flat terrain, they performed just fine. The independent pad adjustment and the simple fact that you can maintain everything with a few Allen keys instead of a bleed kit still make such brakes a valid option. It’s a bit under-geared for me with a 42T chainring and an 11-51T SunRace cassette. I pulled off all the original components, which I’m keeping for the day I want to sell the bike. Instead of the OEM parts, I tuned it up with the components listed below. All in all, I spent CHF 3’200.00 to build the X10 into an X12. At the moment the X12 is set up with a <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/collideous/tags/nox" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">7-year-old</a> Nox Composites Citico wheelset. I will be ordering a pair of Light Bicycle <a href="https://www.lightbicycle.com/700C-gravel-bicycle-rims-40mm-wide-44mm-deep-aero-clincher.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">WG44 rims</a> in August to have them laced up to <a href="https://www.hopetech.com/news/the-all-new-pro-5-hub/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hope Pro 5</a> hubs in early October. A new bike deserves a new pair of wheels.</p>
<table style="border-collapse: collapse; border-color: #7e8c8d; border-style: solid; width: 100%;">
<thead>
<tr style="background-color: #ced4d9;">
<th colspan="3">Info</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>First Ride</td>
<td colspan="2">July 27th, 2023</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bike Weight</td>
<td colspan="2">8.9 kg</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Frame Size</td>
<td colspan="2">Large</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Frame Color</td>
<td colspan="2">Blue / grey</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mileage</td>
<td colspan="2">647.0 km</td>
</tr>
<tr style="background-color: #ced4d9;">
<th colspan="3">Components</th>
</tr>
<tr style="background-color: #ecf0f1;">
<th>Type</th>
<th>Brand</th>
<th>Model</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Frame</td>
<td>Marin</td>
<td>Series 3 Beyond Road</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fork</td>
<td>Marin</td>
<td>Full Carbon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Stem</td>
<td>Syntace</td>
<td>Flatforce TwinFix Torx 44mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Headset</td>
<td>FSA</td>
<td>Orbit IS, tapered</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Handlebar</td>
<td>Easton</td>
<td>EC70 AX Carbon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Seatpost</td>
<td>Easton</td>
<td>EC90 ISA Carbon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Saddle</td>
<td>Prologo</td>
<td>Dimension AGX Nack</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Brake Rotors</td>
<td>Jagwire</td>
<td>Pro LR2, 160mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Brakes</td>
<td>SRAM</td>
<td>Rival eTap AXS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Brake Levers</td>
<td>SRAM</td>
<td>Rival eTap AXS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Derailleur</td>
<td>SRAM</td>
<td>Rival XPLR eTap AXS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cassette</td>
<td>SRAM</td>
<td>Rival XPLR, XG-1251, 10-44T</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Chain</td>
<td>SRAM</td>
<td>Force, CN-FRC-D1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Crankset</td>
<td>Rotor</td>
<td>Aldhu, 175mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Chainring</td>
<td>Wolf Tooth</td>
<td>Drop Stop, 42T</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bottom Bracket</td>
<td>RWC</td>
<td>External BB30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pedals</td>
<td>Crank Brothers</td>
<td>Eggbeater 3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wheels</td>
<td>Nox Composites</td>
<td>Citico</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tires</td>
<td>René Herse</td>
<td>Snoqualmie Pass TC</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Geometry Of A Gravel Bike</title>
        <author>
            <name>Patrick</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://offtrail.guru/the-geometry-of-a-gravel-bike/"/>
        <id>https://offtrail.guru/the-geometry-of-a-gravel-bike/</id>
        <media:content url="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/75/Marin-Gestalt-X10.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="gravel bikes"/>
            <category term="geometry"/>

        <updated>2023-07-23T08:58:32+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/75/Marin-Gestalt-X10.jpg" alt="My Marin Gestalt X10 Built As An X12" />
                    <p>The bikes I ride on pavement or gravel are more than road, all-road, or gravel bikes. They are efficient, practical, surface-agnostic bikes that bridge the functionality gap between road and off-road. In this post, I want to look at the geometry of the bikes I have ridden in the last nine years.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/75/Marin-Gestalt-X10.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="My Marin Gestalt X10 Built As An X12" /></p>
                <p>The bikes I ride on pavement or gravel are more than road, all-road, or gravel bikes. They are efficient, practical, surface-agnostic bikes that bridge the functionality gap between road and off-road. In this post, I want to look at the geometry of the bikes I have ridden in the last nine years.</p>

<p>I started on a red <a href="https://offtrail.guru/volagi-viaje-sl/">Volagi Viaje</a> with 700C wheels in March 2014. The Viaje, introduced on <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/874048428/the-viaje-bicycle-engineered-for-adventure" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kickstarter</a> in August of 2012, was a bike ahead of its time. Its frame and fork had enough clearance for 40mm wide 700C tires and offered plenty of room for 650B <a href="https://www.wtb.com/collections/road-plus" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">RoadPlus</a> tires. It was engineered for adventure. Many today equate adventure with bike-packing, so in this day and age, I would not view the Viaje as an ideal adventure bike. It lacks the many mounting points to carry bags, and the magnificent Long Bow Flex Stays cannot handle much more than the weight of the rider. I loved it, though, and I still do. Born in 2012, the Volagi Viaje had a fairly traditional road bike geometry. It rode like a road bike with a head angle of 72º, a BB drop of 70 mm, short chain stays, and a short wheelbase. It was agile and quick steering. It was fun on <a href="https://offtrail.guru/gravel-grinding/">gravel</a>, but I always had to pay attention to where it was going. This got even more pronounced when I built my third Viaje with 650B wheels. Equipped with smaller wheels, the Volagi Viaje tends to oversteer when leaning into a turn.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://offtrail.guru/nordest-albarda/">Nordest Albarda</a> I built in the fall of 2019 is a different machine. Nordest designed it more along the lines of a comfort bike. A semi-slack head tube angle of 70º and a high 74mm trail result in a bike with a lot of steering stability. One can more easily take the eyes off the road without immediately veering into the ditch. The 28mm longer front center is another good indicator of a well-mannered ride feel. Thanks to the short chainstays and extremely low bottom bracket the Albarda is by no means lethargic. It comes to life at speed. One thing to point out is that I went with a custom geometry because the stock geometry was a bit too upright for my taste. I ordered a medium frame with a 15mm shorter head tube - the head tube of a small. From October 2019 to March 2021, I rode the bike on 700C wheels. In the <a href="https://offtrail.guru/nordest-albarda-2021-update/">spring of 2021</a>, I swapped the groupset from a 2x11-speed SRAM Red eTap HRD to a 2x12 Red AXS groupset and went 650B. This reduces the trail from 74mm to about 68mm and slightly lowers the wheel flop. And it is noticeable! Like the Volagi Viaje, I prefer the Nordest Albarda with 650B wheels.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="5">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/75//gallery/Geometry-Comparison.webp" data-size="2390x1280"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/75//gallery/Geometry-Comparison-thumbnail.webp" alt="Geometry comparison." width="720" height="386"></a>
<figcaption>Geometry comparison.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/75//gallery/Nordest-Albarda-Marin-Gestalt-X10.webp" data-size="2250x1100"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/75//gallery/Nordest-Albarda-Marin-Gestalt-X10-thumbnail.webp" alt="Nordest Albarda vs. Marin Gestalt X10" width="720" height="352"></a>
<figcaption>Nordest Albarda vs. Marin Gestalt X10</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/75//gallery/Volagi-Viaje-Marin-Gestalt-X10.webp" data-size="2250x1100"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/75//gallery/Volagi-Viaje-Marin-Gestalt-X10-thumbnail.webp" alt="Volagi Viaje vs. Marin Gestalt X10" width="720" height="352"></a>
<figcaption>Volagi Viaje vs. Marin Gestalt X10</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/75//gallery/Evil-Chamois-Hagar-Marin-Gestalt-X10.webp" data-size="2250x1100"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/75//gallery/Evil-Chamois-Hagar-Marin-Gestalt-X10-thumbnail.webp" alt="Evil Chamois Hagar vs. Marin Gestalt X10" width="720" height="352"></a>
<figcaption>Evil Chamois Hagar vs. Marin Gestalt X10</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/75//gallery/easton-ax-handlebar-measurements.webp" data-size="1000x735"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/75//gallery/easton-ax-handlebar-measurements-thumbnail.webp" alt="Easton AX handlebar measurements." width="720" height="529"></a>
<figcaption>Handlebar measurements.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>The <a href="https://www.marinbikes.com/bikes/2023-gestalt-x10" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2023 Marin Gestalt X10</a> is a whole different beast. The vast majority of gravel bikes are essentially nothing more than road bikes with room for large tires. The Marin X10 and XR, on the other hand, borrow a lot from modern mountain bikes. And that's why I pulled the trigger and got one. So, what about that geometry? The most eye-popping differences are head tube angle, reach, and a dramatically elongated front-center as a combination of the two. To keep my position, I shortened the stem from 110/100 mm (Viaje/Albarda) to 44 mm. I mounted a wider handlebar to better deal with the very high trail figure and the increased wheel flop. It’s an <a href="https://eastoncycling.com/products/ec70-ax-bar" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Easton EC70 AX</a> in 46 cm. With a 16º flare, the bar has 53 cm in the drops. Maybe also to note, based on Marin’s sizing chart, I’m smack in between an M and an L. I went with a large. The next couple of weeks will show if Marin is onto something with such an MTB-inspired, hard-charging, rough-and-rowdy gravel/adventure bike.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Cycplus Cube Electric Bike Pump</title>
        <author>
            <name>Patrick</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://offtrail.guru/cycplus-cube-electric-bike-pump/"/>
        <id>https://offtrail.guru/cycplus-cube-electric-bike-pump/</id>
        <media:content url="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/74/cycplus-cube-00.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="tools"/>
            <category term="pumps"/>
            <category term="blog post"/>

        <updated>2023-05-27T11:07:49+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/74/cycplus-cube-00.jpg" alt="The toolkit I carry on every ride." />
                    I like shopping on Ali Express. Not so much because it’s cheap, but because I find things no one else sells. Truth be told, I ran across the Cycplus Cube on Youtube first. Cycplus introduced this electric bicycle pump on Indiegogo in February this year.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/74/cycplus-cube-00.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="The toolkit I carry on every ride." /></p>
                <p class="dropcap">I like shopping on Ali Express. Not so much because it’s cheap, but because I find things no one else sells. Truth be told, I ran across the <a href="https://www.cycplus.com/products/tiny-pump-cube" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cycplus Cube</a> on Youtube first. Cycplus introduced this electric bicycle pump on <a href="https://www.indiegogo.com/projects/cycplus-cube-tiny-bike-pump#/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Indiegogo</a> in February this year. The project was fully funded within 12 hours. Cycplus was established in Chengdu, China, in 2014. They make other pumps and also offer various cycling computers. Like many other such companies, they didn’t go to Indiegogo for the funding but to gauge the interest for such a tiny pump. Had I not seen videos of how well this small pump inflates a bicycle tire, I wouldn’t have ordered one from the company’s <a href="https://cycplus.aliexpress.com/store/5796744" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">storefront</a> on Ali Express. But that tiny thing actually works. Like everything else I’ve purchased on Ali Express, the Cycplus Cube arrived at my doorstep in Grenchen, Switzerland in no time. A small package takes an 8'000 kilometer journey and arrives a little over a week later. What a small world! The air intake was the first thing I was confused about when I held it in my hands. The air from the pump’s nozzle must come from somewhere, and I didn’t know from where. I grabbed the small manual to find out that the USB-C charging port is also the pump’s air intake. How cool is that? I charged and then tested the pump by inflating a 29er bike tire. The pump did that in about a minute and a half. I didn’t test how many tires I could inflate on a single battery charge, but based on how quickly it was fully recharged, I think I could have easily inflated another two tires.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="3">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/74/gallery/cycplus-cube-01.jpg" data-size="3026x2161"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/74/gallery/cycplus-cube-01-thumbnail.webp" alt="My toolkit." width="720" height="514"></a>
<figcaption>My toolkit.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/74/gallery/cycplus-cube-02.jpg" data-size="3207x1924"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/74/gallery/cycplus-cube-02-thumbnail.webp" alt="The old and the new pump." width="720" height="432"></a>
<figcaption>Old and new.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/74/gallery/cycplus-cube-03.jpg" data-size="3319x1867"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/74/gallery/cycplus-cube-03-thumbnail.webp" alt="The old and the new pump." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Old and new.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>I know cyclists who don’t carry any tools with them. They have a cell phone and a wife at home who will drop everything to pick them up whenever their bike breaks down. My wife would be mildly annoyed if I would call her each time I needed help. I rather carry a small toolkit with me to help myself. This toolkit used to be heavier. It has gotten smaller as I reduced it to the bare minimum. The Cube has now freed one jersey pocket in which I used to carry a small dual-stage hand pump. I can bring along my <a href="https://offtrail.guru/dji-action-2/">DJI Action 2</a> camera with a small tripod in that free pocket instead.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>A History Of Saddles</title>
        <author>
            <name>Patrick</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://offtrail.guru/a-history-of-saddles/"/>
        <id>https://offtrail.guru/a-history-of-saddles/</id>
        <media:content url="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73/saddles-00.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="saddles"/>
            <category term="cycling"/>
            <category term="blog post"/>
            <category term="bike components"/>

        <updated>2023-04-25T14:34:07+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73/saddles-00.jpg" alt="Prologo Scratch NDR and M5 Nack saddles." />
                    <p class="dropcap">I started mountain biking in 1986 and road cycling in 1992. I don’t remember what saddles were on my first three mountain bikes. I sat on what the manufacturers specced for those bikes. In the early 90ies that changed with Selle Italia’s iconic <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=N9ppbf3UeL0">Flite</a> saddle. It was a minimalist, long, slim saddle with a rounded top and a flexible hull. Equipped with titanium rails it made for a comfortable perch. It was a revolutionary saddle for the time, and I liked it a lot. Over the next decade, I stayed faithful to the brand and moved on to the even more minimalist, narrow-sided SLR. The SLR’s proﬁle ensured minimal pedaling interference, but to be honest, while it felt good with padded shorts or bibs, it was a horrible saddle to sit on without any padding.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73/saddles-00.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Prologo Scratch NDR and M5 Nack saddles." /></p>
                <p class="dropcap">I started mountain biking in 1986 and road cycling in 1992. I don’t remember what saddles were on my first three mountain bikes. I sat on what the manufacturers specced for those bikes. In the early 90ies that changed with Selle Italia’s iconic <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=N9ppbf3UeL0">Flite</a> saddle. It was a minimalist, long, slim saddle with a rounded top and a flexible hull. Equipped with titanium rails it made for a comfortable perch. It was a revolutionary saddle for the time, and I liked it a lot. Over the next decade, I stayed faithful to the brand and moved on to the even more minimalist, narrow-sided SLR. The SLR’s proﬁle ensured minimal pedaling interference, but to be honest, while it felt good with padded shorts or bibs, it was a horrible saddle to sit on without any padding.</p>

<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="4">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-01.jpg" data-size="2635x1883"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-01-thumbnail.webp" alt="Original all black Selle Italia Flite saddle." width="720" height="515"></a>
<figcaption>Selle Italia Flite.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-02.jpg" data-size="3264x2448"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-02-thumbnail.webp" alt="Later generation Selle Italia Flite saddle." width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Selle Italia Flite.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-04.jpg" data-size="3264x2448"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-04-thumbnail.webp" alt="White Selle Italia SLR XC saddle." width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Selle Italia SLR XC.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-03.jpg" data-size="5184x3888"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-03-thumbnail.webp" alt="Black Selle Italia SLR saddle." width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Selle Italia SLR.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>In 2011 I switched brands. I rode <a href="https://www.fizik.com/eu_en/antares-r1.html">Fizik Antares</a> saddles in various models for the next eight years. There were R1, R3 with carbon braided rails or less expensive K:ium metal rails. My 44 Kid Dangerous 29er and my 44 Big Boy fat bike were given the top-of-the-line <a href="https://www.fizik.com/eu_en/antares-00.html">Antares 00</a>. An Antares VS was on my red Volagi, and an <a href="https://www.fizik.com/eu_en/antares-r1-versus-evo.html">R1 Versus EVO</a> still sits on top of my beige <a href="https://offtrail.guru/volagi-viaje-sl/">Volagi</a>. When I rebuilt my <a href="https://offtrail.guru/ritte-snob-disc/">Ritte Snob Disc</a> road bike, I gave it the latest generation Antares 00. The Antares uses a generously proportioned rear and a relatively firm carbon-reinforced shell. Its flat shape meshes well with my anatomy and offers excellent long-distance comfort.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="4">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-05.jpg" data-size="4000x2248"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-05-thumbnail.webp" alt="White and black Fizik Antares R3 with K:ium rails." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>White Fizik Antares R3.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-08.jpg" data-size="3264x2448"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-08-thumbnail.webp" alt="Black and white Fizik Antares R1 with carbon rails." width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Black Fizik Antares R1.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-07.jpg" data-size="5184x3888"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-07-thumbnail.webp" alt="Black Fizik Antares R3 with carbon rails." width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>All black Fizik Antares R3.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-06.jpg" data-size="4000x2248"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-06-thumbnail.webp" alt="Black and pink Fizik Antares R3 saddle." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Pink Fizik Antares R3.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>In 2019 the third saddle transition unfolded with the construction of my <a href="https://offtrail.guru/nordest-albarda/">Nordest Albarda</a>. After years of extra-long saddle designs, several manufacturers introduced saddles with a sawed-off nose. Prologo was one of them with the 245mm short Dimension. That’s 30mm shorter than the Fizik Antares saddles I was used to. The Prologo <a href="https://prologo.it/en/products/dimension-143">Dimension Nack</a> has a big pressure-relief channel, plenty of high-density padding, and a superbly comfortable, stepped nose. It was an immediate love affair. When it came to picking a saddle for my <a href="https://offtrail.guru/stooge-mk5/">Stooge MK5</a> rigid 27.5+ mountain bike, it was a no-brainer that the choice fell onto another short Prologo saddle.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="4">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-09.jpg" data-size="5184x3888"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-09-thumbnail.webp" alt="Special edition Fizik Antares VS saddle." width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Fizik Antares VS.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-10.jpg" data-size="3264x2448"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-10-thumbnail.webp" alt="Black Fizik Antares 00 saddle." width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Fizik Antares 00.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-11.jpg" data-size="4000x3000"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-11-thumbnail.webp" alt="Black Prologo Dimension Nack saddle." width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Prologo Dimension Nack.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-12.jpg" data-size="3623x2233"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/73//gallery/saddles-12-thumbnail.webp" alt="Black Prologo Scratch M5 Nack saddle." width="720" height="444"></a>
<figcaption>Prologo Scratch M5 Nack.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>Because I don’t find open-channel saddles practical for dirt or gravel riding, I selected the <a href="https://prologo.it/en/collections/marathon-xc/products/scratch-m5">Scratch M5</a> for the MK5. Prologo says that the rounded shape of the Scratch M5 allows the pelvis to rotate naturally. It favors the distribution of pressure over a larger surface area, creates stability, and supports the lumbar region. I’m not expert enough to confirm that, but my butt definitely likes sitting on it. My Marin Gestalt X12 will be equipped with the same Scratch M5, while both Fortyfours will say goodbye to the Antares 00 to welcome the latest of the Prologo saddle family, the <a href="https://prologo.it/en/collections/marathon-xc/products/scratch-ndr">Scratch NDR</a> with Nack rails. The ergonomic Scratch NDR is the off-road evolution of the Scratch M5 and is specifically designed for XC and marathon riding.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Vive la Modularité</title>
        <author>
            <name>Patrick</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://offtrail.guru/vive-la-modularite/"/>
        <id>https://offtrail.guru/vive-la-modularite/</id>
        <media:content url="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/modularity-00.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="cycling"/>
            <category term="blog post"/>
            <category term="bike components"/>

        <updated>2023-02-03T18:24:23+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/modularity-00.jpg" alt="Rotor Aldhu spiders and axles." />
                    <p class="dropcap">I now have three sets of Rotor aluminum Aldhu cranks, or four counting the carbon version on my <a href="https://offtrail.guru/ritte-snob-disc/">Ritte</a>. My <a href="https://offtrail.guru/fortyfour-marauder/">Marauder</a> uses an older pair of Rex 1.2, and my <a href="https://offtrail.guru/stooge-mk5/">Stooge</a> sports a current set of aluminum Kapic cranks. Out of seven bikes, six are equipped with Rotor cranks. I love the modularity of Rotor’s cranks with the availability of various axle lengths, different spiders, and a wide selection of round or oval direct mount rings. The only thing I wish they would offer is Kapic axles for fat-bikes.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/modularity-00.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Rotor Aldhu spiders and axles." /></p>
                <p class="dropcap">I now have three sets of Rotor aluminum Aldhu cranks, or four counting the carbon version on my <a href="https://offtrail.guru/ritte-snob-disc/">Ritte</a>. My <a href="https://offtrail.guru/fortyfour-marauder/">Marauder</a> uses an older pair of Rex 1.2, and my <a href="https://offtrail.guru/stooge-mk5/">Stooge</a> sports a current set of aluminum Kapic cranks. Out of seven bikes, six are equipped with Rotor cranks. I love the modularity of Rotor’s cranks with the availability of various axle lengths, different spiders, and a wide selection of round or oval direct mount rings. The only thing I wish they would offer is Kapic axles for fat-bikes.</p>

<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="4">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-01.jpg" data-size="3887x2137"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-01-thumbnail.webp" alt="Rotor Aldhu cranks with BB and spider." width="720" height="396"></a>
<figcaption>Cranks, BB, spider.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-02.jpg" data-size="3635x2119"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-02-thumbnail.webp" alt="Three spiders and two axles." width="720" height="420"></a>
<figcaption>Axles and spiders.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-03.jpg" data-size="3264x2448"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-03-thumbnail.webp" alt="Rotor Rex 1.2 cranks." width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Rotor Rex 1.2</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-04.jpg" data-size="3264x2448"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-04-thumbnail.webp" alt="Rotor Rex 1.2 drive-side crank." width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Drive-side.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>I had a SRAM XX1 fat-bike <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/collideous/32106663527" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">crankset</a> that I had to throw into the trash because the axle was too worn. Well, I sold the drive-side crank for $21.50 on eBay. Only the non-drive side went into the trash bag. I will never buy a set again where one crank is permanently fixed to the axle. Modular cranksets such as Rotor or RaceFace can easily be moved to another bike. You simply buy a new axle if the new bike needs a wider or narrower one. And, if the bearing seats have developed too much wear after several years, you just buy a new axle for less than forty dollars. My <a href="https://offtrail.guru/fortyfour-snakedriver/">Snakedriver</a> now has a pair of <a href="https://offtrail.guru/homework-done/">RaceFace Turbine</a> cranks for that reason.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="3">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-05.jpg" data-size="5184x3888"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-05-thumbnail.webp" alt="Rotor Rex 1.2 with direct-mount chainring." width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Direct-mount ring.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-06.jpg" data-size="4000x2248"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-06-thumbnail.webp" alt="Rotor 3D+ crankset on my Volagi Viaje CX." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Rotor 3D+</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-07.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-07-thumbnail.webp" alt="Rotor Kapic on my Stooge MK5." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Rotor Kapic.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>For my upcoming project, code-named <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/collideous/albums/72177720304814362" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">X12</a>, I’m using a pair of aluminum Aldhu cranks, which have been sitting in my spare parts cabinet for a couple of years. To find the ideal chain line for a 1x12 drivetrain, I purchased three different spiders as well as a standard and offset road axle. The axle not used for project X12 will likely end up on one of the other three bikes. While the 5-arm spider is my favorite, I am going to mount whatever results in the best chain line. I plan to use a Real World Cycling BSA30 bottom bracket for BB cups. It is a spare BB purchased for my Kid Dangerous in <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/collideous/9351279767" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2013</a>.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="3">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-08.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-08-thumbnail.webp" alt="Non-drive side Kapic crank." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Kapic crank.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-09.jpg" data-size="5184x3888"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-09-thumbnail.webp" alt="Non-drive side Aldhu Carbon crank." width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Aldhu Carbon.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-10.jpg" data-size="5184x3888"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/72/gallery/modularity-10-thumbnail.webp" alt="Drive-side Aldhu Carbon crank." width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Aldhu Carbon.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>This is the first time I am mentioning <a href="https://www.strava.com/bikes/11999163" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">project X12</a>. Project X12 is about challenging the tried and true. If it ain’t broke, don’t fix it - If something is reasonably successful or effective, there is no need to change or replace it. German speakers would say “<em>Bewährtes soll man nicht verändern</em>.” When it comes to cycling, most of us stick to that. We ride something, we like it, and we are therefore rarely willing to change it. Project X12 is an inexpensive platform to question everything I know. It may not be “the” answer, but it will certainly provide a ton of answers. And that, for now, is as much as I am saying about this endeavor.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Raudax Cycling Clothing</title>
        <author>
            <name>Patrick</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://offtrail.guru/raudax-cycling-clothing/"/>
        <id>https://offtrail.guru/raudax-cycling-clothing/</id>
        <media:content url="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/71/raudax-clothing-0.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="winter time"/>
            <category term="clothing"/>
            <category term="blog post"/>

        <updated>2023-01-14T16:50:52+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/71/raudax-clothing-0.jpg" alt="Raudax cycling clothing from AliExpress." />
                    With this title, there is a high probability that this post will rank high in the search results whenever someone searches for "Raudax". I have searched for information about this brand myself, and there is very little to find. So, dear visitor, if you happen&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/71/raudax-clothing-0.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Raudax cycling clothing from AliExpress." /></p>
                <p class="dropcap">With this title, there is a high probability that this post will rank high in the search results whenever someone searches for "<a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=raudax+cycling" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Raudax</a>". I have searched for information about this brand myself, and there is very little to find. So, dear visitor, if you happen to land here thanks to a search engine, give me a quick shoutout in the comments below. Anyway, I had a chance to wear the <a href="https://offtrail.guru/shopping-on-aliexpress/">vests I bought</a> on <a href="https://www.aliexpress.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">AliExpress</a> in early November, and they are nice to wear. Everything stays in place when I fill the three back pockets with the items I always carry on a ride. They are not made with a wind-breaking material but from a typical polyester with some stretch. All have already been machine-washed and kept their shape and color.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="4">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/71/gallery/raudax-clothing-1.jpg" data-size="2127x2127"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/71/gallery/raudax-clothing-1-thumbnail.webp" alt="Camouflage thermal cycling jersey by Raudax." width="720" height="720"></a>
<figcaption>Jersey by Raudax.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/71/gallery/raudax-clothing-2.jpg" data-size="2052x2801"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/71/gallery/raudax-clothing-2-thumbnail.webp" alt="Camouflage thermal cycling vest by Raudax." width="720" height="983"></a>
<figcaption>Vest by Raudax.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/71/gallery/raudax-clothing-3.jpg" data-size="2374x2374"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/71/gallery/raudax-clothing-3-thumbnail.webp" alt="Thermal winter jacket by Raudax." width="720" height="720"></a>
<figcaption>Jacket by Raudax.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/71/gallery/raudax-clothing-4.jpg" data-size="2155x2155"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/71/gallery/raudax-clothing-4-thumbnail.webp" alt="Camo vest over winter jacket." width="720" height="720"></a>
<figcaption>Jacket and vest.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>With that positive experience, I bought three more items from a different vendor at the end of December. This time I filled my shopping cart with a long sleeve jersey, a jacket, and a vest with a thermal fleece for winter temperatures. All three are made by <a href="https://www.aliexpress.com/store/5885239" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Raudax</a>, a Chinese brand that sells its products primarily on AliExpress. Just like the three vests purchased in November, there is nothing to complain about. The zippers appear to be good quality, and the garments are neatly sewn. The fabrics feel great, and the fit is right. They are sized a bit large, but I generally wear two or even three layers underneath a jacket in the winter. So a relaxed fit is just what I need for the outermost layer of clothing. If the remainder of winter stays as warm as it has been, I will sadly not get a chance to wear them. And since I cannot travel, I cannot go where the snow is.</p>
<ul>
<li>2023 Raudax Winter Cycling Thermal Fleece <a href="https://www.aliexpress.com/item/1005004948247790.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Jacket</a> - CHF 16.94</li>
<li>2023 Raudax Winter Cycling Thermal Fleece <a href="https://www.aliexpress.com/item/1005004953041850.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Vest</a> - CHF 14.38</li>
<li>2021 Raudax Winter Cycling Thermal Fleece <a href="https://www.aliexpress.com/item/1005003198368423.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Jersey</a> - CHF 17.31</li>
</ul>
<p>For a total of <strong>CHF 57.60</strong> including shipping.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>A Pair Of Tires With Bite</title>
        <author>
            <name>Patrick</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://offtrail.guru/a-pair-of-tires-with-bite/"/>
        <id>https://offtrail.guru/a-pair-of-tires-with-bite/</id>
        <media:content url="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/70/tires-with-bite-00.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="tires"/>
            <category term="stooge mk5"/>
            <category term="blog post"/>

        <updated>2023-01-08T11:08:54+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/70/tires-with-bite-00.jpg" alt="Stooge MK5 with a pair of new tires." />
                    <p class="dropcap">When I first set up my <a href="https://offtrail.guru/stooge-mk5/">Stooge MK5</a> in March of last year, I mounted a pair of Schwalbe <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/collideous/51316999643" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nobby Nic</a> 27.5x3.0” tires. For 3” wide tires, they were light, coming in under 900 grams. They climbed and cornered well but had one shortfall. As a rear tire, the Nobby Nic performed poorly when braking in steep terrain. The tire broke loose too quickly. I rode into stuff a few times where I had to get off the bike to get down that segment of trail safely. I would have easily ridden it with a better tire. For my second season on the Stooge, I’ve opted to equip it with a more aggressive pair of tires.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/70/tires-with-bite-00.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Stooge MK5 with a pair of new tires." /></p>
                <p class="dropcap">When I first set up my <a href="https://offtrail.guru/stooge-mk5/">Stooge MK5</a> in March of last year, I mounted a pair of Schwalbe <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/collideous/51316999643" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nobby Nic</a> 27.5x3.0” tires. For 3” wide tires, they were light, coming in under 900 grams. They climbed and cornered well but had one shortfall. As a rear tire, the Nobby Nic performed poorly when braking in steep terrain. The tire broke loose too quickly. I rode into stuff a few times where I had to get off the bike to get down that segment of trail safely. I would have easily ridden it with a better tire. For my second season on the Stooge, I’ve opted to equip it with a more aggressive pair of tires.</p>

<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="4">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/70/gallery/tires-with-bite-01.jpg" data-size="3690x2777"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/70/gallery/tires-with-bite-01-thumbnail.webp" alt="Duro Crux 27.5x3.25" width="720" height="542"></a>
<figcaption>Duro Crux</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/70/gallery/tires-with-bite-02.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/70/gallery/tires-with-bite-02-thumbnail.webp" alt="Duro Crux 27.5x3.25" width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Duro Crux</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/70/gallery/tires-with-bite-03.jpg" data-size="4032x2268"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/70/gallery/tires-with-bite-03-thumbnail.webp" alt="WTB Bridger 27.5x3.0" width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>WTB Bridger</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/70/gallery/tires-with-bite-04.jpg" data-size="3765x2118"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://offtrail.guru/media/posts/70/gallery/tires-with-bite-04-thumbnail.webp" alt="Stooge MK5 with a new pair of tires." width="720" height="405"></a>
<figcaption>Stooge MK5</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>Up front, I mounted the largest tire the steel fork can swallow, a Duro Crux at a whopping size of 3.25”. I popped on a 3.0” wide WTB Bridger in the back. In 2021, I bought four of these from <a href="https://www.chainreactioncycles.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Chain Reaction Cycles</a> for $14.00 a piece. Both these tires weigh considerably more than the Nobby Nic. The WTB Bridger is a few millimeters narrower, but interestingly, it is a good centimeter taller than the German Schwalbe. Visually, it is easy to see that the bike now rolls on a lot more rubber than last year.</p>
<p>Because the bike industry abandoned 27.5+ tires in 2016, I stocked a bunch of tires for my Stooge. For the next few years, I have:</p>
<ul>
<li>2 Duro Crux 27.5x3.25” (1 mounted)</li>
<li>4 <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/collideous/51328351798" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">WTB Bridger</a> 27.5x3.0” (1 mounted)</li>
<li>2 <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/collideous/51317516614" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kenda Havoc Pro</a> 27.5x3.0”</li>
<li>2 <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/collideous/51316055147" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Specialized Ground Control</a> GRID 2Bliss Ready 6Fattie 27.5x3.0”</li>
<li>1 <a href="https://www.wtb.com/products/trail-boss-3-0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">WTB Trail Boss</a> 27.5x3.0" (from a recent NOS purchase on eBay)</li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
